Hi, I'm Amy Goodman. Stay tuned now for Tell Somebody with Tom Clammer.
Prisons in our country, courses, there are no college courses anymore.
Lied even to those of us inside the CIA.
This week on Tell Somebody, whistleblower and former CIA officer John Kiriakou
Peace activist Brian Terrell's remarks last Sunday at the gates of Whiteman Air Force Base.
Stand by for Tell Somebody.
Hello and welcome to Tell Somebody for May 21st, 2015, www.telsombody.us
On Twitter at TellSomebodyNow
And on Facebook.com slash TellSomebodyNow
Please like that page and remember you can subscribe to the podcast for free at the iTunes store.
This is your host Tom Clammer. It's good to be back after two weeks off.
Big thanks to Bill Claus and Craig LeBeau of KKFI's Radioactive magazine for filling in with wonderful guests on a couple of great shows.
And thanks as always to your old pal and mine, Mike Murphy.
Mark your calendars, folks. KKFI's next pledge drive is coming up real soon.
Looks like Tell Somebody's Day will be Thursday, June 4th, 9 a.m. Central Time.
I hope you'll make plans to tune in and call in with your support for Independent Community Radio and for Tell Somebody.
And I'd like to point out to all the podcast listeners in over 90 countries around the world, you can play too.
You can stream the show live at KKFI.org and whether you do that and listen live or if you only listen by podcast, you can click on the donate button at www.KKFI.org.
Make your donation and add a note on why you appreciate Tell Somebody.
Before we get rolling with the rest of the show, a quick note from Stand Up KC about an event coming up later this morning, just under two hours away.
They write, Join us this Thursday, May 21st, 11 a.m. for a minimum wage rally to stand with working families.
We will meet at the front steps of City Hall in downtown Kansas City, Missouri to rally before the City Council hearing at noon.
And that will be 414 East 12th Street in Kansas City, Missouri, 64106.
And they say, We know that when working people come together, we have the power to make change.
On with the show.
Once again we will hear some of Brian Terrell's remarks from last Sunday's drone protest at Whiteman Air Force Base.
But first, from Wikipedia, John Kiriakou is an associate fellow with the Institute for Policy Studies and a blogger for Huffington Post.
He was a CIA analyst and case officer, senior investigator for the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and counterterrorism consultant for ABC News and an author of several books.
He was the first U.S. government official to confirm in December 2007 that waterboarding was used to interrogate al-Qaeda prisoners.
And he described that as torture.
On October 22, 2012, Kiriakou pleaded guilty to disclosing classified information about a fellow CIA officer that connected the covert operative to a specific operation.
He was sentenced to 30 months in prison on January 25, 2013 and served his term from February 28, 2013 until February 3, 2015 at the Low Security Federal Correction Facility in Loretto, Pennsylvania.
I called him at his home in Arlington, Virginia.
Give a listen.
John Kiriakou, welcome to tell somebody.
Very glad you're able to take the time. We appreciate it.
So you've been home for a while. You were in prison and then under house arrest.
But you're totally free now, is that right?
I was reading about your house arrest conditions and I'm sure it was great to get out of actual full incarceration.
But these seem like pretty harsh methods. Can you talk about what kind of restrictions you were on there?
And if I remember right, it seems like it took a couple hours, three, four hours, out of just about every day to do this?
Yeah, at first I had to go to the Tapway House every day and of course the job get a job.
This is just almost Kafkaesque weird, it seems to me.
That's what I called it. I called it Kafka and send you back to prison.
And how typical is this kind of craziness for people getting out of prison generally?
Do a lot of people with maybe less ability to deal with it than you had have to deal with this kind of thing?
That's a very important question and the answer is a resounding yes.
Utilitate no one and they train no one. Courses, there are no college courses anymore.
You've got to go with what you know, huh?
You've got to go with what you know and they're always on your back about being able to provide for your family.
And for a lot of guys who know nothing else and really have no job skills, provide for their families, the only thing they can do is to sell them.
Well, we could do a whole show or two on that and we do have some shows on this station that do that.
But I'm wreaking havoc with any kind of chronological telling of your story.
Before we get to some of the CIA stuff, can you briefly tell me what the actual in prison part of your experience was like?
Prosecution had agreed to it and so when I bring to my paperwork or not, and so I went to the actual prison motion with the court,
it would probably take years to get a hearing, so I just formation act for quick.
I could determine why.
The sphere of a lot of these folks, I'm afraid, isn't it?
There's so many things I want to ask you, but given the shortness of time, I want to make sure we get what you did,
what they say you did, what you were convicted of.
Can you find a starting point for that tale and what were the charges and what's your take on what you did and so forth?
That torture was official U.S. government policy, right?
He said we $100,000 fine in 18 months of...
$100,000 fine that Tray said to pay.
Yes, he ordered his normal speaking fees.
Yeah, I was just going to say, that'd be a lot of money for a lot of us, including me.
But he's just donated part of one of his speeches.
That's amazing.
I was going to ask you what you thought of his sentence and compared to yours,
and then what was this latest one, Sterling?
General Petraeus, as much as General Petraeus should have been charged with a crime,
for the same reason that I shouldn't have been charged, one of us had any criminal intent.
And secondly, neither one of us caused any harm to the national security.
General Petraeus is friends with the president and so he got a sweetheart deal.
I didn't get a sweetheart deal and neither did Jeffrey Sterling.
Now, Jeffrey Sterling was a CIA case officer, an operations officer,
who was accused of providing information about a botched CIA operation
to provide flawed information to Iran's nuclear program
by using a Russian side operation to the House Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence
into their heads.
He's rising. He's never said that he maintained that he was not a sore conversation.
Just metadata indicating that emails had been exchanged.
Espionage, the information, had been present because of this verdict,
which I thought was just insane.
Both in Sterling's case and in your case was the Espionage Act.
I believe it was in your case. What about this?
Yeah. We were bomb-drank with charge with Espionage.
Count to the Espionage.
Declassify solely for the purpose of prosecuting me.
Tell you now what it was, seven years.
Kaida, in fact, we were killing members of all Kaida
and we were trumpeting it on the front pages of every newspaper in America.
But the CIA said that that information had never been formally declassified
with Espionage.
Lower Tom Drake's Espionage charges were drawn to target German saboteurs
during the First World War.
It was updated very briefly in 1950 in the aftermath of the Julius Neffler-Rosenberg case.
Now, I think it's been often mentioned in the press the number of times this has been used.
This was 1917 law that through the end of World War I, through World War II,
through the Cold War, three times it was invoked and Obama was Sterling the Eighth?
Sterling was the Ninth.
Ninth? Okay.
Yeah. Espionage Act was invoked.
And was all of your prosecution initiated and carried through in the Obama administration
or did any of it start with Bush?
Yeah, mine was solely Obama determined.
Obama was inaugurated.
How did you first become aware that the U.S. was engaging in torture?
The CIA's Chief of Counterterrorism Operations in Pakistan.
When I got back, Counterterrorism Center, what he called certified
in the use of enhanced interrogation techniques, that meant I had never heard
of enhanced interrogation techniques before.
So I asked him, well, we're going to start getting rough with some of these guys
and here's what we're going to do.
And he described these torture techniques to me.
And I said, whoa, I don't think that's for me.
That sounds like torture.
I have a moral problem with it and I'm not interested.
I guess that was in June of 2002.
Well, by July or early August, maybe it was early August,
we started hearing stories and reports from friends of mine in the CIA
that we were engaging in torture.
We were torturing up as a beta, for example.
And you were told these torture techniques work, but they really didn't,
as far as I know.
They didn't.
You know, and this is another thing about the CIA,
is the CIA lied even to those of us inside the CIA.
And the reports from the field said that torture worked,
that out of the beta had cracked,
and that he gave us information that saved American lives.
Found that that just simply wasn't true, that torture did not.
We're not saved.
Senate Torture Report.
And, you know, I guess in some important moral sense,
it doesn't matter whether they work or not, we shouldn't do them.
But the people saying that it works, they just can't really back that up.
Second question is, is it not, is it resounding now?
On that line, a lot of us have heard Seymour Hersh's,
if we haven't read the whole long article,
we've maybe seen an interview on Democracy Now!
or heard about his debunking of the Bin Laden capture and kill story.
I think I read something online that you are a bit skeptical of,
at least some parts of that,
but the CIA working with the filmmaker of Zero Dark Thirty
and giving this strong impression that torture led to the finding the location
and taking out Osama Bin Laden.
Any comments on all of that?
Yeah.
I mean, he does have something of a track record,
and I forget the woman's name,
but there's somebody else that had a similar story out much earlier than that.
And these Hersh's and Hersh's stories don't jive in every detail,
but in large measure they do, right?
The Bin Laden killing was just simply not true.
I agree.
I know you have to go in a few minutes,
but you have a website and you have plans for going forward from this point.
Could you give us the website and a little bit about what you want to do now?
Any other final words you want to leave with our listeners before I let you go?
Oh, thanks.
I don't mean to sound like what Spiro Agnew once called a mattering neighbor of negativism,
but after 19 years in government,
I can tell you that you really can't trust me.
Okay, well I guess for now we'll leave it at that.
I'd love to talk to you again
and get into more detail on some of these things somewhere down the road,
but really appreciate you taking the time tonight.
John Kiriakou, thank you very much.
Thanks for having me.
Sounds good.
John Kiriakou, that's K-I-R-I-A-K-O-U-W-W-W.JohnKiriakou.com.
We need to play a message or two for you right now
and we'll be right back after you listen.
Welcome back to tell somebody this is Tom Clammer.
Last Sunday, Missouri peace activists rallied at the entry to Whiteman Air Force Base
near Nob Noster, Missouri.
The aim?
To oppose drone warfare and to seek peace.
Brian Terrell, co-coordinator of Voices for Creative Nonviolence, spoke at the rally.
Terrell served six months in a federal prison camp for resistance at Whiteman Air Force Base in 2012.
With help from Mike Murphy, Jane Stover recorded Brian Terrell's talk and got a copy to me.
Apparently a few folks on motorcycles made a little noise now and then
to register their disapproval of the peace rally.
Give a listen.
On April 21st and on April 26th, we were together in Northern California,
Beale Air Force Base, another drone base, and Kathy and I and 14 others were arrested there.
She knows we're here today and she sends her greetings.
The morning that she's going to be arrested?
Yeah, yeah, the prison, it just doesn't work, does it?
Some alternatives like a government that doesn't commit war crimes.
That might be the only way that's going to stem it.
On my way to Beale, before that I was at a meeting in Las Vegas
planning more demonstrations for Creech Air Force Base.
We're back in March, some 200 people gathered, camped outside of Creech Air Force Base,
the center of the Air Force and CIA drones, and 32 of us were arrested.
The resistance is growing and so is the general dis-ease about this.
In Las Vegas on my way to Beale, you probably all remember this April 23rd television
and for the first time in my lifetime, because I'll be talking about two,
it brings some things into focus.
The president used the excuse of the fog of war.
No, our combat veterans, but I think we don't need to imagine
just what that mix are made when people are in the field, in the jungle,
in the desert, for weeks at a time.
It should not happen in Beale, in Al-Qaeda.
This article, at times, spooned the people.
Smoke is clearing the fog of war around the long Guantanamo.
We know that there were about 800 prisoners there, all told.
They were all gathered.
They're the ones on Rumsfeld said that they were the worst of the worst.
That 800 was called out of thousands and thousands who had been imprisoned
in Badram, Abu Ghraib, lots of other black sites we don't even know about.
We're brought to Guantanamo.
Right now, there are about 140 left.
Even though these people were not allowed trials, but were being,
had their cases heard by military tribunals, secret proceedings,
evidence gained by torture, except all those numbers that they let go
were people that they had nothing on.
They finally said, even with everything stacked against them,
no real defense.
We got the wrong people.
And they let go.
Well, unfortunately, what, five have died,
number have died in custody.
Okay, then out of that number, there are more than 36
who have been cleared for release.
And the reason they're not being released is totally political.
The United States, the military and the CIA admit we have nothing on these people.
We don't know anything about them,
that they ever have been a danger to the United States.
And they should be let go, but no one will take them.
And Congress is doing what it can to block their release.
There's another like 36 people who have not been living
also selective prosecution because it's against the law to make excessive noise.
You know, because of the noise.
But they're not going to...
Should I call Missouri? I would try.
Yeah, call 9-1-1 and report it down.
No, we don't need to do that.
It's just tragic.
And I think it is very indicative that
their tactic is to make noise to drown out
to drown out the discussion.
Not to engage, but to shut it up.
Because once you have this discussion, there's only one place that can go.
And I think ultimately they know that.
So they don't want to hear.
So anyway, there's like 36 people there too
who are still there and a Guantanamo
who will probably be there if the Pentagon has its way.
They will be there forever.
And out of these 36 men,
they did nothing that we know of before they were arrested,
before they got to Guantanamo.
They were never a threat to the United States.
They would never hurt any of us.
But now, for 12 years, they've been in solitary confinement,
they've been force fed, they've been tortured.
They can't let them go because they might hurt us.
And this is not my take on it.
This is what the Pentagon says about why these people cannot be released.
So these are the people,
the people who made the decision about who would go to Guantanamo
are the exact same people.
And if you look up this article in the Times, it names them.
These are the exact same people who are now targeting,
deciding who's going to die.
So when you hear that a bad guy got killed,
in Al-Qaeda, this Fruq Akhmet Farrouk,
that he was a bad guy, that he was an accomplice with Al-Qaeda,
take it with a grain of salt because we don't know
and there was no indictment, there was no charge.
This is just assassination.
These are simply murder victims, all of them.
These strikes, no matter what it is they did,
as Patrick could tell you as a lawyer,
it's against the law to kill a gangster on the street.
No matter how bad somebody is, they should have a trial
and you just can't kill them because you feel like it,
because you think they're bad or they look like somebody who's bad.
This strike, they killed these two American citizens
and this Italian man and how many others,
what they call a signature strike,
they're simply looking at the patterns of behavior
and deciding that because people were acting a certain way
around this building there must be something nefarious going on in there.
So the strike happened.
It's exactly as reflected in our cities with racial profiling.
So anyway, I'm glad you're here.
Get in touch with me, I'll get in touch with,
get things on your email list about coming up.
April 1st is going to be another shutdown preach,
it's great to come and camp out with us in the desert,
it's a beautiful time of the year to be there
and to keep coming here because this is a rising tide
and it's something that I do believe is making a difference.
So thank you very much.
Thank you.
Brian Terrell speaking at Whiteman Air Force Base
in Missouri last Sunday.
Some of the folks who joined Brian at Whiteman
will be walking and or writing between Kansas City's old
and new nuclear weapons parts plants on Memorial Day.
This Monday, May 25th, starting at 8 a.m. at the old plant
at 95th Street or Banister Road and Lydia
and then heading south about 10 miles to the new plant.
If you'd like to join them or just want to find out more about it,
there is information at www.pieceworkskc.org
or get to your calendar on Facebook
and find the event page for the Memorial Day Walk and Ride.
Well, that's it. We're out of time.
You've been listening to the podcast edition of Tell Somebody.
www.telsombody.us
Comments or questions, send an e-mail to mail at telsombody.us.
You can also follow me on Twitter at Tell Somebody Now.
The Tell Somebody podcast is produced and distributed by Tell Somebody
and may or may not reflect the broadcast of Tell Somebody
heard on 90.1 FM KKFI in Kansas City
streaming around the world at www.kkfi.org.
I'll be on 90.1 FM KKFI every Thursday morning
at 9, right after Democracy Now.
If you haven't heard Tell Somebody before, I hope you'll listen again.
Check out the podcast and the broadcast.
Click on a tile at www.telsombody.us for a link to a past show.
If you enjoyed the show and appreciated the information you got from it,
please tell somebody about the podcast and the broadcast.
Spread the word to your friends in contacts by word of mouth
or Facebook or Twitter or e-mail list
or any other way you can think of.
This is Tom Klammer. I'll see you next Thursday at 9 a.m. on Tell Somebody
or any time you'd like at www.telsombody.us.